When the kaiju appeared and you told me to run,
怪兽出现后，你叫我快跑
if you didn't save me then,
那时，如果不是你救了我
I would've died today.
我今天早就死了
I really think you should be a Defense Force officer.
你果然该去当防卫队员
Thanks, Ichikawa.
谢谢你，市川
I knew it. You're a really good guy.
你果然是个好人啊
I'm going to try joining the Defense Force again--
我要再次立志成为防卫队…
I found you.
找到你了
Kai… Kai…
怪…
Senpai!
前辈！
"It'll be okay.
“放心吧
Anytime that happens, I'll be right next to you!"
到那个时候，我会一直陪在你身边”
Wow, Kafka-kun! You read too much manga!
不是，卡夫卡，你看太多漫画了啦
That was so corny!
笑死我了
You bastard!
你这家伙
Don't say a word about this to our moms, all right?
绝对不要跟我妈和阿姨说哦
Those two are always oversharing with the other moms.
她们一定会马上告诉朋友的
Thanks.
谢谢
It's not so scary when it's the two of us.
两个人一起，确实就不会害怕了呢
The kaiju was discovered in the hospital.
怪兽是在医院发现的
We must prevent any human casualties.
务必在有人受害之前…
We'll defeat this kaiju at all costs.
把怪兽打倒
A small kaiju has appeared in Yokohama.
横滨市出现小型怪兽
I repeat.
重复一次
This alert is so annoying!
这个警报好吵哦
-Why can't the government change it? -Hurry, Sho-chan!
-政府就不能换个声音吗？ -小翔，快一点
All civilians should immediately evacuate to a shelter…
所有市民请尽快前往避难所
-Shut off the lights. -…lock all doors…
-把灯关了吧 -紧闭门窗
…and take all life-saving measures…
请采取保护生命安全的行动
It's all a misunderstanding!
对了，先解开误会吧
-Senpai, smile! -Smile?
-前辈，微笑 -微笑？
Right. Got it. Smile.
微笑对吧？
Oh, shit. This won't work.
啊，这绝对行不通
I knew it!
果然！
You all right, gramps?
老爷爷，你没事吧？
I did this to him? I'm seriously a kaiju!
是我做的吗？ 这样子不就是真的怪兽了吗？
-What is it? -An explosion? Are you okay?
-怎么了？ -爆炸吗？还好吗？
Is that a kaiju?
欸，那是怪兽吗？
Officers are on their way.
防卫队员要来了
Let's run!
我们快逃吧
Right. We don't want to cause more trouble for the hospital.
说的也是 不能再给医院造成更多麻烦了
Let's leave through this window!
从窗户逃走吧
I knew it!
你看吧
What's going on with this body?
这身体到底发生什么事了？
-Call the doctor, now! -Let's run, senpai!
-快叫医生 -要逃了，前辈
What?
什么？
Hey! Wait!
喂，等等！
The kaiju escaped from South Yokohama General Hospital.
怪兽从横滨南综合医院逃走
It's heading towards an Evacuated Area.
正朝向避难区前进
What the hell's going on?
到底是怎么回事？
Senpai turned into a kaiju?
前辈变成了怪兽？
Since when? Why?
从什么时候？为什么？
Anyways, is that even a kaiju?
话说回来，那算是怪兽吗？
I want to confirm this just in case.
以防万一，我确认一下
You really are senpai, right?
你真的是前辈吧？
I'm not so sure myself!
我自己也不清楚啊
What the hell is that? You transformed!
那是什么啊？什么模式吗？
I want to know myself!
我才更想知道啊！
Look, Ichikawa! I'm eating a live bird!
市川，快看，我在吃活生生的鸟！
So gross! You're really gross, senpai!
好恶心！超恶心的，前辈！
-Oh, I turned back. -Your transformations are gross!
-啊，变回来了 -变回来的方式也很恶！
-I really need to pee. -Right now? Hold it in!
-我超想尿尿的 -现在？请你忍一下
This body's going to pee no matter what!
不是，是这副身体想尿啊
I can't do anything to stop it!
我也没办法
I don't want to.
不要啊
I'm a human, an adult. I don't want to pee in public!
我一个人类、一个大人 怎么可以在大马路上尿尿？
Where is it going to come out of? I can't find any holes.
你要从哪里尿？ 好像也没看到那个东西…
-Senpai! -No one will marry me anymore.
-前辈！ -我嫁不出去了！
I'll die right here!
让我就地往生吧！
There are other things to worry about right now!
不，还有更重要的事情要担心吧？
Come on. Let's go!
好了，快走吧！
Hey, Ichikawa.
但是啊，市川
What's going to happen to me now? Could I join the Defense Force?
以后我会变成怎样呢？ 还能当上防卫队员吗？
There's no way!
不行
You're on the side of being neutralized. You'll be killed on the spot!
你怎么看都是被讨伐的对象啊 会被当场处决的
Right? I knew it!
也是哦
Huh? In that case…
咦，也就是说…
There's no way I'll ever become a Defense Force officer.
我已经无法成为防卫队员了吗？
Shit! After I swore to myself that I'll catch up to her!
可恶，明明已经决定 要再次追上那家伙
How could I, with this body?
这副身体要怎么…
Senpai!
前辈
ROAD CLOSED
（禁止通行）
This is a restriction line. There won't be any civilians beyond this point.
是封锁线，进去之后 应该就没有人了
-Senpai? -Quiet. Someone's coming.
-前辈？ -安静，有什么要来了
An officer?
防卫队员？
No, it's from underground.
不…是从地下
This is…
这是…
Another kaiju?
另一只怪兽？
Cart 2, continue forward.
2号车继续前进
We'll head to a new point.
我们前往新地点
This is the same species that attacked us.
和昨天袭击我们的是同一种
You can tell?
你分得出来吗？
But this will split the number of officers assigned to attack you.
这样一来，分配到 前辈这边的队员就减少了
Now's our chance to hide!
是藏身的好机会
Luckily, all civilians have been evacuated from your report.
幸好因为前辈出现 居民都已经先去避难了
Let's hope there are no victims!
希望不会出现受害者
Mom!
妈妈！
Run…
快逃…
quickly…
快点…
Give me a second. I'll save you!
等等哦，我马上来救你
-Run! -I won't go without you!
-快跑！ -不要！我要和妈妈在一起！
Run… please…
快逃…求求你…
Please. Please!
求求你…
Please!
求你了…
-No! Mom! -Please!
-不要，妈妈！ -求你了
So powerful!
好强的威力
You okay?
没事吧？
Right, sorry about that. Well…
也对，抱歉，那个…
-Smile! -No!
-微笑 -不要！
I'm sorry!
啊，对不起
I'll go away! Don't cry!
我马上就走。拜托你别哭了
-Senpai! -Yeah.
-前辈 -哦
Mom!
妈妈…
She's just unconscious. She'll be fine.
她只是昏倒而已，没事的
-Really? -Yeah.
-真的吗？ -真的
Ichikawa, look after those two.
市川，那两个人就拜托你了
What are you doing?
你想做什么？
I'm going to punch him for real.
我想稍微认真地试一拳
Step back!
离远一点
One, two…
一、二…
Three!
三！
That was…
这是…
Something you should never do to humans.
绝对不能对人用的招式
Senpai?
前辈？
It'll be all right.
已经没事了
Take her to the hospital.
快把你妈带去医院…
Listen. The Defense Force will be here any minute.
听好了，防卫队马上就到了
I'll go away. You'll feel better then.
我也会马上离开，放心吧
Kaiju-san?
怪兽先生？
Thank you.
谢谢你
Thanks.
谢谢
It's not so scary when it's the two of us.
两个人一起，确实就不会害怕了呢
Yeah! We'll be stronger together!
没错，两个人一起的话
Let's go!
走吧
Right.
没错
I have to go.
我一定要过去
Senpai! I just called the emergency services.
前辈，我叫救护车了
Let's go before they arrive.
在其他人来之前，快走吧
Senpai?
前辈？
Ichikawa. I decided not to give up.
市川，我果然没办法放弃
I have to be by her side.
我一定要到那家伙身边去
What happened here?
这到底是…
What the hell is this?
这是怎么回事啊？
Tell me about the kaiju you saw.
把你看到的怪兽告诉我们吧
Kaiju.
怪兽
It'll be okay.
放心吧
I'm going to defeat all the kaiju.
我会把怪兽全部消灭的
Really?
真的吗？
Please don't defeat that nice kaiju-san, though.
可以不要打倒温柔的怪兽先生吗？
He saved my mom.
他救了我妈妈
A SKETCH BASED ON WITNESS ACCOUNTS
（根据目击者描述绘制的画像）
Kaiju No. 8.
怪兽8号
This became the eighth kaiju with a code name
这个生物已成为防卫队用代号命名的
provided by the Defense Force.
第八只怪兽
No. 8 remains on the run,
目前8号仍然行踪不明
-and the Defense Force is on high alert… -They haven't found him yet?
-防卫队仍维持高度警戒… -还没找到这家伙啊？
Right?
就是说啊
Maybe it's dead already.
会不会已经死了？
This became a bigger deal than we expected.
彻底闹大了呢
WITNESS - AGED 103
（男性目击者，103岁）
Three months have passed. Senpai became the first unneutralized kaiju
在那之后，过了三个月 前辈成为了防卫队成立以来
since the founding of the Defense Force.
首次未讨伐成功的事件
He's now pursued by Defense Force officers around Japan.
也是全日本防卫队员追缉的对象
Right, Ichikawa.
对了，市川
This was delivered to you and Kafka.
这是寄给你和卡夫卡的
He had the morning shift, so he's on-site.
那家伙上早班，已经去现场了
-Take this to him. -Yes, sir.
-你就拿去给他吧 -好
It's already that time of year, huh?
已经是这个时节了啊
Kafka used to apply every year.
卡夫卡以前每年都会参加测验呢
It's an annual event.
例行公事
Along with the "sorry-you-didn't-pass" party afterward.
然后就是安慰大会呢
YOU HAVE PASSED THE PRELIMINARY ROUND…
（您已通过第一次测验…）
-Nice. Great job! -As expected of you!
-哦，干得好 -真不愧是你
Thanks.
谢谢
Should I take this to Kafka?
还是我来把卡夫卡的拿去吧？
No, it's all right. I'll bring it to him.
不，没关系，我来就好了
-Looks like he passed, too. -But this year is his last chance.
-看来他有去考呢 -不过，今年是最后一次吧
God, I really hope he makes it.
最后的机会，要是能抓住就好了
He's been working hard for so many years.
那家伙一直很努力啊
Senpai!
前辈！
We passed the preliminary round!
我们通过第一次测验了！
Seriously?
真的吗？
Why are you all exposed?
你为什么原形毕露啊？
Isn't it too early to be this violent?
一大早这样，不会太激烈了点吗？
Your face! Do you even know what's going on?
你的脸啦，你知道现在什么情况吗？
Shit. It still comes out without me realizing.
糟糕，现在还会在 不知不觉间变成这样
-All good now! -Not good at all!
-这样就没问题了 -并没有变回去啊！
You were on the news just now, in the office!
我刚刚在办公室还看到新闻了
You have to be more careful!
请你有自觉一点！
Got it, got it. I'm sorry!
我知道啦，对不起
As for senpai and me…
我和前辈…
-You're the patients! -Are you all right?
-你们是病房的伤患 -你们没事吧？
Yes, we're fine.
对，没事
We told them we evacuated after being shocked by the kaiju.
后来被当作被怪兽吓到，去避难了
Looks like no one knows yet, but…
总之，似乎并没有穿帮
This is yours, senpai.
给你，这是前辈的
SELECTION RESULTS
（选拔结果通知）
YOU HAVE PASSED THE PRELIMINARY ROUND…
（您已通过第一次测验…）
Oh, good. I'm glad.
哎呀，真是太好了
I thought you would be happier.
我以为你会更高兴一点
I always get rejected in the second round!
我都是在第二次落选的
Why do you look so proud?
为什么一脸得意？
So, what's your plan?
那你打算怎么办？
You really intend on going to the second round with that body?
你真的要用那个身体 参加第二次测验吗？
It'll be okay! I'll hide it really well!
没问题啦，我会隐藏得很好的
That's not reassuring!
完全没有说服力！
Preliminaries are just documents and written exams.
跟只有书面审查和笔试的 第一次测验不同
There'll be a bunch of officers at the second round!
第二次测验应该会遇到许多队员
You could get killed on the spot--
要是被发现，会被当场处决的
Even so, I'm going.
就算这样，我也要参加
I did a bunch of research in the three months we had,
那之后的这三个月虽然做了许多调查
but I couldn't find any way to turn back my body.
但也没找到复原的方法
I'm 32 now. This year's round of applications
对32岁的我来说，这次测验…
is truly my last shot.
是实际意义上的最后一次
JAPAN DEFENSE FORCE RECRUITING OFFICERS
（日本防卫队，队员招聘中）
I understand.
我明白了
But no matter what happens to you, I'm going to keep pushing forward.
但要是前辈出了什么事 我也会继续前进的
You're my rival, after all.
既然要参加，那我们就是对手了
This cap is so tight!
盖子好紧
I take it all back! Don't take the exams!
前言撤回，你果然还是不行！
Wait, I'll be okay!
等等，没问题的
-I'll hide it better during the exams! -Let me go!
-正式考试时，我会藏得很好的 -放开我！
Don't abandon me!
不要丢下我
I won't help you, no matter what!
说真的，不管变成怎样 我都不会帮你的
Everyone's arriving soon. Pull yourself together!
大家应该都快到了，请你好好注意！
I'm so glad! If he passed and I didn't,
太好了，只有我落选的话
I would've failed as a senpai!
这个前辈的面子就挂不住了
All right. Time for a rematch.
好，我要一雪前耻
UNDERGROUND PARKING LOT
（地下停车场）
DEFENSE FORCE SCREENING EXAM SECOND ROUND WEST TOKYO HALL
（防卫队员选拔第二次测验 西东京会场）
MONSTER SWEEPER INC.
（怪兽清扫有限公司）
Wow.
好厉害
So, this is the Defense Force's Tachikawa Base.
这里就是防卫队立川基地
It's much bigger than the Kumagaya Base that I visited on a field trip.
比之前社会课 参观过的熊谷基地还要大
This is attached to the Japan Ground Self-Defense Force base.
毕竟这里和 陆上自卫队的屯驻地并在一起嘛
During emergencies,
出现状况时
they work together to dispatch officers all around West Tokyo.
他们会互相联系 并派遣队员到西东京中央
If you transformed right here, you'd never survive.
在这种地方变身的话，会被秒杀吧？
Freaking out won't help us. Let's go!
害怕也没用，上吧
-Hey, old man. -We're a bit early,
-喂，大叔 -虽然还有点早
but let's go sign in.
我们先去接待处报到吧
-Listen, old man! -Senpai.
-我说大叔 -前辈
Yes, I'm talking to you.
没错，就是你
Took you long enough, old man.
快给我反应过来啊，大叔
OLD MAN?
（大叔？）
Huh? Me?
咦，我吗？
She's an applicant, too?
这女孩也是考生吗？
I'm not old! I'm still 32!
我才不是大叔，我才32岁！
-So, you are old. -I am?
-那不就是大叔吗？ -是这样吗？
She's not wrong.
嗯，是这样
That piece of junk is yours, right? It's in the way.
那辆破车是你的吧？很碍事
I can't park my car there. Move it over.
我的车没办法停了，请你移开
-This lot is super empty! -I want to park there.
-这里不是超空的吗？ -我想停在那里
My lucky number of the day is five.
因为我今天的幸运数字是5
Lucky number of the day, you say?
你说幸运数字？
You spoiled little girl…
这臭屁小丫头是怎样？
Come with me!
你过来
This young man will teach you a thing or two about manners.
哥哥来教你“礼貌”两个字怎么写
Fine. I'll move it myself.
算了，我自己来吧
Geez, what are you doing?
喂，你突然间做什…
That suit…
这套战斗服是…
That's company property!
公司的车！
Who are you?
你到底是谁？
I'm applicant number 2016.
准考证号码2016号
Kikoru Shinomiya. My hobby is killing kaiju.
四之宫琪歌露，兴趣是杀怪兽
Remember my name, all right?
给我记好了
Shinomiya! That means her family is…
四之宫，这个姓是…
Forget that. Hey, old man.
对了，大叔
You smell like kaiju.
你好像…有股怪兽的臭味？
Subtitle translation by: Yukimi Ohashi
字幕翻译：唐咏杰